Guide to the Lowell Joseph Ragatz papers, 1821-1872 MS0887.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Lowell Joseph Ragatz papers
1821-1872
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS0887.UA
1 Linear Feet
Collection of handwritten notes from Washington newspapers that had articles dealing with the University and its history. This included commencements, advertisements, medical, law and other GW schools. The collection covers the years 1821 to 1872.
Box 1
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
This collection was part of the original materials accessioned into the University Archives in 1987. Before that time they probably resided in the office of University Historian Elmer Louis Kayser.
Historical or Biographical Note
Lowell Joseph Ragatz (1897-1978) was a professor of history at George Washington University from 1924-49, and served as chairman of the department from 1934-37. After receiving a preliminary education at his home town of Prairie Du Sac, Wisconsin, Ragatz went to the University of Wisconsin where he earned a B.A. degree in 1920, M.A. degree in 1921, and Ph.D. in 1925. He continued his graduate study at the University of Pennsylvania in 1921-22, the University of Grenoble in 1922, University of Paris in 1922-23, College of France in 1922-23, Ecole Libre des Sciences Politiques in 1922-23, and the London School of Economics in 1923.
He was teaching fellow at the University of Wisconsin in 1920-21 and at the University of Pennsylvania in 1921-22 before coming to GW in 1924. He was a delegate to the second Congress of the Pan-American Institute of Geography and History, a lecturer at the War Department in 1942 and the Lend- Lease Administration's African Mission Training School at Washington, D.C. in 1943 (the lecture was published as Introductaion to French West Africa and Introduction to French North Africa), and a consultant with the U.S. Information Office in London during 1947-48.
Dr. Ragatz was regarded as a pioneer of African studies in the United States and also was one of the first professors who used audio-visual aids in university education. He was a member of the American Historical Association, the American Association of University Professors, the Inter-American Bibliographical and Library Association, Societe d'Histoire Moderne, Societe d'Histoire des Colonies Francaises, Phi Beta Kappa, Ominicron Delta Kappa, Pi Delta Epsilon, Pi Gamma Mu, Phi Alpha Theta, Acacia, the Free and Accepted Masons.
Dr. Ragatz edited twenty-eight volumes for the American Historical Association from 1929-42, and authored seventeen books from 1922-62. He was awarded the Justin Winsor Prize of the American Historical Association in 1926 and a Guggenheim Fellowship for 1933 and 1934.
Dr. Ragatz was a elected to the American Philatelic Society Hall of Fame in 1979 and was a life-long student of philatelic fakes, forgeries and bogus stamps. Using the pen name, "George Van Den Berg," his "Philatelic Notes" column was published in Stamps from 1933 through the early 1960s. The column was devoted to stamp collecting, collectors, and the changing philatelic customs of those times. He was lauded for his long membership in the Society of Philatelic Americans which he joined in 1910 when it was the Southern Philatelic Association. Dr. Ragatz died October 29, 1978.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials from the collection include handwritten notes from Washington newspapers that had articles dealing with the University and its history. This included commencements, advertisements, medical, law and other GW schools. The collection covers the years 1821 to 1872.
Collection Organization
Arranged chronologically.
Audiotapes; Commencement ceremonies -- Washington (D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Ragatz, Lowell J. (Lowell Joseph); Columbian College in the District of Columbia; George Washington University--History; Columbian University
- Articles, 1821-1822 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General note
  Opening of the University, first examination, etc.
- Articles, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Advertisements, finances, Baptist convention, examinations, etc.
- Articles, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Summary of operations, Board of Trustees actions, Congressional relations, fundraising, Pres. Staughton's trip abroad, faculty, library purchases, act of incorporation, arrival of Lafayette in Washington, first commencement, idea of Columbian College as a national institution, etc.
- Articles, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Congressional relations, new construction, Medical School, President Monroe, second commencement attended by Pres. of U.S.
- Articles, 1826-1829 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Law Department, fundraising, medical school, Pres. Chapin and his inaugural address, Congressional relations, commencement.
- Articles, 1830-1835 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Lectures on chemistry, student fees, Columbian Academy (Preparatory School see Kayser's Bricks Without Straw), commencement, Pres. Staughton's career, Thomas Sewall, etc.
- Articles, 1836-1840 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Regulations, class sessions, French literature, medical school, description of college, commencement, advertisements.
- Articles, 1841-1845 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Medical school commencement, advertisements for medical school, commencement, Board of Trustees, class sessions, Preparatory School.
- Articles, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Commencement, Preparatory School, class sessions, etc.
- Articles, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Advertisement, medical school, Enosinian Society, commencement, Alumni of Columbian College, class sessions.
- Articles, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Preparatory School, class sessions.
- Articles, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Preparatory School, class sessions, commencement, etc.
- Articles, 1850-1852 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Commencement, class sessions, medical school (National Medical College), advertisement, etc.
- Articles, 1853-1857 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Commencement, National Medical College, College building, class sessions.
- Articles, 1862-1866 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Civil war, commencement, National Medical College, hospital, W.W. Corcoran.
- Articles, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Law school commencement, Preparatory School commencement, commencement.
- Articles, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  National Medical College, Law School commencement, Preparatory School commencement, commencement.
- Articles, 1869-1872 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Medical School commencement, Law School commencement, Amos Kendall.
- Articles, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Lowell Ragatz correspondence with Pres. Marvin, location of university buildings to GW.